Today's דף daf is ע"ה ayin hey as you see you've got
a lot of חומשים chumashim open in front of you because we're
going to have to look at the פסוקים psukim a little bit
and we start with the גמרא Gemara at the very bottom of
ע"ד עמוד ב'. ayin daled amud bet. The משנה Mishnah spoke about
how you make the מנחות, menachos, that's for you, all those חומשים
chumashim are for you. Okay how you make the מנחות menachos and
it said that all the מנחות menachos you first put oil in
the vessel then you put in the flour and mix it with
oil and then you do יציקה yetzikah you pour oil on afterwards.
So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, however introduced it
by saying that this is true by all מנחות menachos that are
made in a vessel. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
למעוטי מאי, l'ma'utei mai, what does that excluding when it says made
in a vessel? What type of מנחות menachos does this not apply
for? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa,
so רב פפא Rav Pappa says למעוטי מנחת מאפה l'ma'utei minchas ma'afeh
to exclude the baked the oven מנחה. minchah. Now it's a little
bit strange that it's saying that the oven מנחה minchah was not
made in a vessel because first of all you would make it
in a vessel beforehand, you would mix it, the oven is a
vessel. You would right, you would mix it with oil beforehand, I
mean the גמרא Gemara talks before about the fact that if it's
שתי הלחם shtei halechem or לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and you baked
it, since they didn't have oil so maybe they didn't require כלי
שרת k'li shareis because you didn't have to measure out the amount
of oil. But here by the מנחת מאפה תנור minchas ma'afeh tanur
in the תורה Torah it actually does have oil, so number one
that's strange and as Michael says number two is the oven is
a vessel
and you know the מפרשים meforshim really struggle with this. תוספות Tosafot
says well maybe this is of the opinion the oven was not
a כלי שרת, k'li shareis, but still so what you wouldn't make
the מנחת מאפה תנור minchas ma'afeh tanur in any type of a
vessel. It's hard to understand how we're squeezing that into the words
to say that when the משנה Mishnah says anything made in a
vessel we're excluding a מנחת מאפה. minchas ma'afeh. One of the מפרשים
meforshim of the רמב"ם Rambam because the רמב"ם Rambam actually says that
a מנחת מאפה, minchas ma'afeh, a baked מנחה minchah you know an
oven מנחה minchah was made in a vessel. It says no no
no we don't mean to say that it's not made in a
vessel, we mean when it says anything made in a vessel it's
somehow implying that we're not talking about everything. So what we really
mean is well we're going to exclude something even though it is
made in a vessel. I don't know, if that didn't make sense
I didn't understand it either. It just means that by saying everything
that's like this has this הלכה halakhah the suggestion is is that
there are things that don't have this הלכה. halakhah. The problem is
is that the thing that we're excluding fits the criteria as well.
So I really don't understand that and don't ask me to explain
it anymore because it's not I don't have another explanation but for
now the key is not to understand why it doesn't fit in
the criteria of made in a vessel which it seems to, but
just to understand what we're saying is this would be the easier
thing for us, let's not try to squeeze it into those words
but let's understand what we're saying when the משנה Mishnah says these
three stages for standard מנחה, minchah, oil in the vessel then you
put in the flour and you mix with new oil and then
you add oil at the end, that is by the מרחשת marcheshes
and the מחבת machavas and not by and by the מנחה minchah
of the סולת, soles, so there are and but not by the
מנחה minchah of the oven. Okay and we're going to discuss in
a minute how the oven מנחה minchah was made. Right let me
just one minute let me just I know you're very interested in
your book there okay but hold on right I know but it
still doesn't explain how fits into the משנה. Mishnah. Let me just
also say by the way so it's clear and then we're going
to look in the פסוקים psukim in a minute there are four
types of מנחות. minchos. There's a מנחת סולת minchas soles which is
just flour and oil and it's not baked. It's actually interesting that
you know as you remember when we discussed last time the תורה
Torah never speaks about water but גמרא Gemara assumes you added water.
The רמב"ם Rambam does not have water in the מנחת סולת minchas
soles I noticed last night when reading it again and that could
make sense because if you're not baking it then how do you
stop it from becoming חמץ? chametz? So the רמב"ם Rambam actually has
that as just having flour and oil and that you know if
there's no water it can't become חמץ. chametz. Anyways that's the מנחת
סולת. minchas soles.
What do they do with it?
What do they do with it? You mean they they mix it,
they make it into dough then they put some on the מזבח
mizbe'ach and the כהנים kohanim eat the rest.
Eating it raw? What? They don't bake it, they don't bake it.
That's the מנחת סולת. minchas soles. Well they can bake it on
their own, they can bake it on their own but the way
it's brought is just dough. That's the מנחת סולת, minchas soles, it's
a dough מנחה, minchah, that's it, flour and oil, okay that's the
dough מנחה. minchah. Then you have מחבת machavas and מרחשת marcheshes which
are more like frying type of things, a flat frying pan a
deep frying pan, those are those and those are like the משנה
Mishnah says you put oil in the vessel, you put in the
flour, you add you add oil, you mix it, you add water,
those could become חמץ, chametz, then you fry it in two different
ways of frying. That's מחבת machavas and מרחשת. marcheshes. So those are
two and three and fourth type is מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur which
is more like we think of just bread, you bake it. Okay
so there you add oil you add water you make a dough
you put it in the oven and you bake it. Okay that's
מאפה תנור. ma'afeh tanur. So what we are saying is these three
stages oil in the vessel then mixed in oil then oil afterwards
does not apply to the מנחת מאפה תנור minchas ma'afeh tanur and
we will decide we we the aspect in particular that does not
apply is the pouring of the oil afterwards. So let's keep on
reading a little bit we have to get a little bit further
in the גמרא Gemara to fully get this but at this stage
what we're saying is is that oven baked מנחה minchah you do
not put oil on after after the. afterwards after you're done with
the whole mixing and baking like you do by the rest. Okay
so let's take a look at how we get this from the
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*: ואם מנחת מרחשת
marcheshes, קרבנך *v'im minchat marcheshet corbanacha* קרבנך סלת בשמן תעשה *corbanacha soles
bashamen te'aseh*. So now let's look at the פסוקים pesukim. *psukim* that
I have so nicely opened up in front of here, okay, and
I just described to you the four types of מנחות minchos, *menachot*,
which are in ויקרא *Vayikra*.
And here's what we have the following. So it starts with פרק
ב' עמוד א' amud Aleph. *Perek Beis Amud Aleph* בנפש כי ki,
תקריב קרבן מנחה korban minchah לה' סלת יהיה קרבנו *benefesh ki takriv
corban mincha l'Hashem soles yihey corbano*, so that's מנחת סלת *minchat soles*,
that's flour. ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבנה *v'yatzak aleha shemen v'natan
aleha levonah*. Okay, so that's just flour and oil. You put on
it oil and then you add the לבנה *levonah*, flour and oil,
that's סלת *soles*. Now you look at the next פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*,
at פסוק ד' pasuk daled, *pasuk daled*. וכי תקריב קרבן korban מנחה
mincha מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur, *v'chi takriv corban mincha ma'afeh tanur*, so
this is the baked one. סלת חלות chalot, מצות בלולת בשמן ורקיקי
מצות משחים בשמן *soles chalos matzot blulot bashamen urkikey matzot m'shuchim bashamen*.
Various loaves and wafers, we'll get back to that, let's bracket that
for a minute. Now look at פסוק posuk? ה' Hei *pasuk hey*.
ואם מנחה mincha על המחבת HaMachvas, קרבנך *v'im mincha al hamachavat corbanacha*,
if it is on a frying pan, סלת בלולה בשמן מצה matzah,
תהיה *soles blula bashamen matza tiyeh*, so you mix it with oil
and then make it מצה matzah *matza*. And פסוק posuk ז' *pasuk
zayin* is ואם מנחת מרחשת marcheshes, קרבנך *v'im minchat marcheshet corbanacha* סלת
בשמן תעשה *soles bashamen te'aseh* with oil. So now what we are
going to do is the following. We're going to look specifically at
the מחבת machvas *machavat* and מרחשת marcheshes. *marcheshet* and get from this
the idea that there are three placements of oil by the standard
מנחות minchos *menachot*, not the מנחה mincha *mincha* of מאפה *ma'afeh* but
the other three מנחות menachos. *menachot*. How? If you look at the
מחבת machvas *machavat* it says in פסוק posuk ה' *pasuk hey*: ואם
מנחה mincha על המחבת קרבנך סלת בלולה בשמן *v'im mincha al hamachavat
corbanacha soles blula bashamen*. So you mix it with oil. You look
at the מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet* it says סלת בשמן תעשה *soles bashamen
te'aseh*, in oil, which means that there's oil, the way the חז"ל
*Chazal* understand it is there's oil beforehand and then you put the
flour on top of the oil. So if you combine the מחבת
machvas *machavat* and the מרחשת marcheshes, *marcheshet* and learn them from one
another, you get that there was oil beforehand, that's בשמן *bashamen*, and
then after there's oil beforehand you add oil בלולה בשמן *blula bashamen*.
Now where do you get the pouring of the oil afterwards, right,
we will talk about that in a minute, but that's what we
get the first two stages.
Okay so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to discuss.
Let's take a look. Okay so let's look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. But this is by the מחבת machvas, *machavat* and the מרחשת
marcheshes, *marcheshet*, we're going to then have to talk about the other
two מנחות Minchos *menachot*. תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*: ואם מנחת
מרחשת marcheshes, קרבנך סלת בשמן תעשה *v'im minchat marcheshet corbanacha soles bashamen
te'aseh*, in oil you shall make it, מלמד שטעונה מתן שמן בכלי
*melamed shete'una matan shemen bekli*. First you have the oil and then
you put the flour. קרבנך קרבנך *corbanacha corbanacha* לגזירה שוה *ligzeira shava*.
And it says קרבנך *corbanacha* here by the מחבת machavas *machavat* and
it says קרבנך *corbanacha* by the מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet* so you link
the two. מה להלן מתן שמן בכלי אף כאן מתן שמן בכלי
*ma lahan matan shemen bekli af kan matan shemen bekli*. So the
same way by the מרחשת marcheses. *marcheshet* it says that you start
with the oil, that's true by the מחבת machavas *machavat* as well.
ומה להלן יציקה yetzika ובלילה אף כאן יציקה yetzikah, ובלילה *uma lahan
yetzika uvlila af kan yetzika uvlila*. And the same way there too
there is mixing and pouring, here too there is mixing and pouring.
Now where is there mixing and pouring? Oh, thank you.
Thank you.
So one minute because if you look at the מחבת machavas *machavat*,
right, I ended it one פסוק posuk *pasuk* earlier. Look at the
מחבת machavas, *machavat*, it's מנחה minchah מחבת machavas קרבנך סלת בלולה בשמן
*mincha machavat corbanacha soles blula bashamen*, you mix it with oil. And
then it says, פתות patot, אתה פתים pitim, *patot ota pitim*, so
after you've baked it, what do you do? Let's look again. Let's
read פסוק Pasuk, ה' *pasuk hey* and ו' *vav*. Let's read the
מחבת Machavas, *machavat*, that is the one that is true of the
three stages. ואם מנחה mincha על המחבת קרבנך *v'im mincha al hamachavat
corbanacha*, you're making it on a frying pan, סלת בלולה בשמן מצה
matzah תהיה *soles blula bashamen matza tiyeh*. You mix it with oil,
and then חז"ל *Chazal* understand you also add water or else you
wouldn't have the possibility of חמץ chametz *chametz*. Okay and then you
make, so now you fry this thing, this dough that was mixed
with oil and water. Afterwards, פתות patot. אתה פתים pitim *patot ota
pitim*, break it into little into pieces, ויצקת עליהם שמן *v'yatzakta aleihem
shemen*. And after you fried it and broken it into pieces, now
you pour oil on top of it. So you get it, you
fry it, you have this hard whatever it is, you know, wafer
type of oily thing, you break it into pieces and you pour
oil on top. So from the מחבת Machavas *machavat* we have that
you mix it with oil and you pour oil on top. From
the מרחשת Marcheshes *marcheshet* we have that the oil was already in
the כלי kli *kli*. So if you combine the מחבת Machavas. *machavat*
and the מרחשת Marcheshes *marcheshet* we have the three stages. You start
with the oil in the כלי kli *kli*, you put the flour
in, you add the oil, you fry it or you deep fry
it, break it into pieces, pour oil on top. So that we
get by combining the two. Now we are going to assume that
that applies to the dough one, although interestingly the dough you don't
have a frying process, a baking process, but nevertheless we're going to
assume those three stages, but we're not going to apply it to
the oven one. And we'll talk about that in a little bit
when we get to describing what the oven one did consist of.
Okay so let's now go back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. חלות
בלולן chalot belulan, דברי רבי Rebbi וחכמים אומרים סלת *chalos blulan divrei
Rebbi v'chachamim omrim soles*. Now where are you? I'm back into the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*.
No, but where?
three lines from the top of ע' ה' עמוד א'.
Okay, now, now, now, excuse me,
we just said that what do you do? After you bake it,
what do you do? You pour oil on top of it, right?
So the question is, when do you do the mixing with oil?
What I described to you is, that first you mix it with
oil and you make a dough that has oil in it, then
you bake it, then you break it into pieces, and then you
do a little pouring afterwards, the יציקה afterwards. When רבי Rebbi says
חלות challas בלולן, he's talking about that middle stage, the בלילה, belilah,
the fundamental mixing with oil where there's a lot of oil and
you're really mixing it all together. And רבי Rebbi says you do
not do that when it's at the dough stage. You don't do—I
mean, you don't do that at the flour and oil and you
mix it and you make an oily dough like I described. But
what רבי Rebbi says you do is, you bake it with just
flour and water. You bake it with a simple dough. After it's
made a simple dough, then you break it into pieces, then you
add a lot of oil and the mixing with oil, the serious
mixing, not just the little pouring, the serious mixing with oil comes
after it's been baked and then it's being mixed with oil. Now
it doesn't sound that way from the פסוקים. pesukim The פסוקים pesukim,
say, אם מנחה על המחבת קרבנך סולת בלולה בשמן מצה תהיה. im
mincha al hamachavas korbanacha solet belulah bashemen matzah tihyeh. It says סולת
בלולה בשמן. solet belulah bashemen. Right? Flour mixed with oil, not the—not
the baked pieces mixed with oil. Okay, רבי Rebbi is getting what—his—his
indication more from what the תורה Torah says by the מאפה תנור,
ma'afeh tanur. but we're not talking about the מאפה תנור. ma'afeh tanur,
By the baked oven it says, וכי תקריב קרבן מנחה מאפה תנור
סולת חלות מצות בלולות בשמן. vechi takriv korban mincha ma'afeh tanur solet
chalot matzot belulot bashemen. There it says flour, baked חלות, challas mixed
with oil. So he is saying, ah, we see over there it
sounds like you're actually mixing the baked product with oil. So in
general the בלילה, belilah, the mixing, that important middle stage whereas where
the most of the oil is the—is, that happened after it's baked
and not when it's flour. Okay, so we're going to—רבי Rebbi, is
going to be rejected. Not only is the—do the Rabbis reject רבי,
Rebbi the תוספתא Tosefta says it in the end רבי Rebbi wound
up abandoning his position and agreeing to the Rabbis. So it's a
strange position, but let's take a look at it. Okay? So anyway,
all right, so let's take a look at it. Okay. Yes. Are
you—are you lost already in all this?
Or—I'm sort of settling in for all this level of
detail, wondering—it's a—it's a recipe. Exactly.
Well, yeah, I'm kind of wondering about that because I understand why
they'd have to go into details for an animal קרבן korban because
you don't do those things in real life, right, with animals?
Well, sprinkling blood and that type of thing, right.
But here, this is just baking, domestic, right?
This is just bring flour,
bring—but the תורה Torah describes four different types. If it's this type
of מנחה mincha. you bake it this way, if it's that type
you bake it that way. The תורה Torah describes different types, so
you know, look, it's sort of like saying if I want to
bring a sheep, why do I care if it's male or female,
if it's one year old or two years old or three years
old? No, if you want to bring this type of קרבן korban?
it has to be this type of an animal and this age
and this gender. And if you want to bring this type of
a מנחה mincha it has to be, you know, this type of
a—this type of it has to be, you know, this type—this type
of flour, this type of oil, made this way. Why is it
different than which type of gender and age the animal?
I'm—I'm not sure, but it—it—it has—it has
a
feel of more details
than
necessary.
Well, because here you have to do it, whereas by the animals
you just have to find—identify the right animal, whereas here you have
to actually construct something. The interesting thing here is by the way
that number one is a lot of this might be able to
be done without a כהן kohen depending on when you introduce the
כלי שרת. kli sharis. And number two is, the—in the end the
הלכה halacha is going to be that if you didn't do almost
any of these details you're still יוצא. yotzei.
So that makes it—that makes it easier. Okay.
All right. So anyway, all right, so let's take a look at
רבי's Rebbi position. סולת בלולה מלמד שנבללת סולת. solet belulah melamed shenivelelet
solet. So תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, סולת בלולה, solet belulah, so you
mix it while it's still flour, right? That's when you add the
oil. רבי אומר חלות בלולן. Rebbi omer chalot belulan. You mix it
with when they are already baked, שנאמר חלות בלולות shenemar chalot belulot
by the מנחה mincha, of the מאפה תנור, ma'afei tanur,
which is not our מנחה mincha, that we're discussing now anyway, but
that for him is the paradigm. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
to him, והלא לחמי תודה נאמר בהן חלות vehalo lachmei todah nemar
bahen chalot one minute, but the bread of תודה todah it also
says you bring them as loaves and mixed with oil, נאמר בהן
חלות nemar bahen chalot and ואי אפשר לבלולן כשהן חלות. ve'i efshar
levololan keshehen chalot.
You can't mix them when they are loaves. Now why not? Because
there's a lot of loaves of תודה, todah, there are 40 loaves
of תודה todah and if you do the math which רש״י Rashi
does for you but I won't or whatever, you basically have about
a quarter of a לוג, log, רביעית revi'is of a לוג, log,
which is I don't know like three ounces of oil for 20
loaves. So there he's saying it is impossible, you know, once you
bake something it's very absorbent. So if you think you have to
take the baked loaves and add add oil after it's baked and
mix it so that you get a nice sort of like, what's
it called, coherent thing like that the oil it all fits together.
You're not going to succeed to do that if you have 20
loaves and like three ounces of oil. So clearly you're not adding
the oil after the loaves, you're adding some oil during the flour
and you're also adding water to the flour and that's how you're
making it. So the oil is added during the flour stage not
during the loaf stage. So that's, so now we're going to see
how they would describe the process differently. אלא סולת, Ella soles, but
you add it when it's flour. כיצד עושה, Keitzad oseh, how do
you do this? נותן שמן בכלי קודם לעשייתן, Nosain shemen bikli kodem
la'asiyasan, following our משנה, Mishnah, first you start with oil in the
vessel,
right? ונותנה, venosnah, and then you put the flour, ונותן שמן עליה,
venosain shemen aleha, then you put oil on the flour. Now, of
course what is missing here, very importantly because it's not in the
תורה, Torah, but has to go in there if we want the
possibility of חמץ chametz. and מצה, matzah is you also add some
water, okay? ובללה, uvollalah, and that
so you do the mixing with the flour and the oil, while
it's flour, you mix it, ולשה, velashah, and then you knead it,
ואופה, veofah, ואופה, veofah, I guess and you bake it, ופותתה, ufosetah,
then פתות אותה פתים, posos osah pisim,
after it's baked you break it into little pieces, then ויצקת עליה
שמן. veyatzakta aleha shemen.
That's the end of the פסוק. ונותן עליה שמן, venosain aleha shemen,
then you pour a little oil on the broken pieces, וקומץ, vekomaitz,
you do a
and you do a קמיצה. kmitzah. By the way, this is why
you have to break it into pieces, because if you have to
do a קמיצה, kmitzah, how are you going to do a קמיצה
kmitzah after it's baked? You have to break it into little pieces.
Okay, that's what the, that's what the חכמים Chachamim say. רבי אומר
חלות בלולות. Rebbi omer chalos belulos.
Nope, you add you do the real mixing with oil when they're
already baked. שנאמר חלות בלולות
בשמן. shene'emar chalos belulos bashemen. כיצד עושה, Keitzad oseh, how do you
do it? נותן שמן בכלי קודם לעשייתן, Nosain shemen bikli kodem la'asiyasan,
I agree that you start with oil in the vessel. Then ונותנה,
venosnah, you put the flour, and no oil now. You just the
flour. Now of course not just the flour, you gotta have water
because we're going to make it a dough, but no extra oil
now. ולשה, velashah, you do you knead it, ואופה, veofah, and you
bake it, ופותתה, ufosetah, then you break it into little pieces. Then,
now that you have little pieces of basically bread, then ונותן עליה
שמן ובללה, venosain aleha shemen uvollalah,
now you put the serious amount of oil and you mix it
all together. Now and now you have like one big, you know
sort of coherent mass of, you know little bread pieces combined by
with oil. Then, that's the בלילה. belilah. Now that you've done the
בלילה, belilah, then we have to do ויצקת עליה שמן. veyatzakta aleha
shemen. חוזר ונותן עליה שמן וקומץ. Chozer venosain aleha shemen vekomaitz.
And then you do the oil and then you do the קמיצה.
kmitzah. Okay, so,
so therefore you have רבי Rebbi, that does the By the way,
the amount of oil that you would put is the standard amount
of flour would be an עשרון, issaron, which I think we figured
was roughly a five pound bag, I could do the math again,
but something like that, of flour. And the amount of oil is
a לוג log for every עשרון. issaron. A לוג log is about
14 ounces, give or take. Because a רביעית, revi'is, which is the
amount that we have on שבת, Shabbos, is a רביעית revi'is of
a לוג. log. So a לוג log is four times that. The
amount of שבת Shabbos is about three and a half ounces, is
how big your cup should be, your קידוש kiddush cup on שבת.
Shabbos. So it's about 14 ounces. So 14 ounces of oil for
a five pound bag of flour. So obviously, you're also adding water
to make dough and the oil and so on, but that amount
is as we say, not like רבי, Rebbi, is at the flour
stage with the water, not after it's baked to try to make
it to try to combine all of the bread pieces.
You can make a couple loaves from five pounds of flour. What?
You can make a couple loaves, a lot of loaves.
A lot of loaves, I imagine, I imagine. How much does like
how much flour goes into like one one חלה? challah?
One חלה, challah, one pound? One pound?
Four cups?
Four cups? And how many cups would you say is in a
five pound bag?
Oh god, a lot.
I total up total lot of times.
Okay, all right.
This is based on my mother-in-law's חלות challos, after some observation. They
do. They do. I'd say she makes
about five חלות Challos, from one bag, was it like a five
pound?
Yeah, five pound bag. Okay. All right. So that's roughly what we're
talking about.
And we're going to talk about where all this took place. Is
there was there a bakery?
Yeah, so that's the thing. There was an oven. I mean, it
partly goes where the oven is, כלי שרת. kli shareis. We keep
on deferring that discussion. I do think it is coming up. I
know, because it's all the question of, is the כהן kohen doing
it, is the ישראל Yisrael doing it, is it in a כלי
שרת? kli shareis? Is it not in a כלי שרת? kli shareis?
And we always sort of like alluding to it but never focusing
on it. I think a more focused discussion is coming up. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, אי אפשר דקאמרי ליה רבנן לרבי
מאי היא? Ee efshar deka'amri lei Rabbanan leRebbi mai hee?
When the רבנן Rabbanan say, oh, it's impossible to think you add
the oil later if you're dealing with the תודה. Todah. Why is
that impossible? So אמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, Amar Rebbi Shmuel
bar Rav Yitzchak, רביעית שמן היא, revi'is shemen hee, because the amount
of oil that you add to 20 of the loaves of the
תודה, Todah, basically you divide the תודה Todah into 40 loaves and
whatever however the math works, 20 of the loaves gets a רביעית
revi'is of oil, which is like three and a half ounces, היך
מתלחלחת. heich mislachlachas.
there is no way that after they're baked and they're absorbent that
you could do anything significant with three ounces of oil with 20
loaves of the תודה. Todah. So therefore,
it clearly was not added at the after the bake stage, it
was added at the flour stage. Okay. So now,
just one second.
Right. Okay. So now we go on. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So now what do we know? We know that
by
a מחבת Machvas and a מרחשת, Marcheshes you add the oil, you
put in the flour, you add the oil with the flour, like
the חכמים, Chachamim, not like רבי, and water. So you make a
doughy, an oily dough, I guess. Look, it's the same way when
we make bread, right, we tend to add eggs, right, but you
can bake
a cake with oil.
With oil, right. Okay. So and then you bake it, or whatever,
not you bake it, you fry it, if it's a מחבת Machavas
or מרחשת, Marcheshes break it into little pieces, pour some oil on
afterwards. Now we are going, that's the מחבת Machvas. and the מרחשת.
Marcheshes Now we go back to the חלות, challos, because remember we
said by the מאפה תנור, Ma'afeh Tanur the oven-baked one, that you
do not do the pouring of the oil afterwards. Now we're going
to clarify how it is that you do the oven-baked ones. So
let's take a look.
חלות, challos the loaves, the oven-baked,
טעונות בלילה te'unos belilah ורקיקין משיחה. ve'rekikin meshichah. So if you look
at the פסוקים, pesukim let's look back at our פסוקים psukim here.
So if you look at פסוק ד', וכי תקרב קרבן מנחה מאפה
תנור, vechi takriv korban minchah ma'afei tanur, if you bring a קרבן
korban מנחה mincha. which is baked in the oven as opposed to
now we've been talking about fried, different types of frying,
סלת חלות מצות בלולות בשמן, soles challos matzos belulos bashemen, so it
either could be חלות, challos which is flour with oil, or ורקיקי
מצות משוחים בשמן, ve'rekikei matzos meshuchim bashemen, or wafers anointed with oil.
So the way the גמרא Gemara is going to understand it is
this is the basic difference between the חלות challos and the wafers.
The חלות challos you make the dough, you do the flour with
the oil, and then you bake it. That's, this is all baked
in an oven. Okay, so it's basically, you know, it's basically חלה
challah just it has oil in the dough. That's בלולות בשמן. belulos
bashemen. The wafers you don't put any oil in beforehand, you bake
them in the oven, and after they're baked, then you put the
oil on afterwards. So basically the basic difference between the חלות challos
and the רקיקין rekikin is that the חלות challos have the oily
dough, the dough has the oil added at the time. The רקיקין
rekikin are baked simply as a water חלה challah essentially, funny why
it's called רקיקין, rekikin, and then the dough is added afterwards. Okay,
the dough, the flour, the oil, the oil, starting ingredient is added
afterwards. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara And that's
why the גמרא Gemara says that by the baked ones, you don't
have the יציקה, right? It says by the normal fried ones, you
all pour oil after, but here, the whole difference of the two
types of loaves for the baked is that when do you add
the oil? So we don't have the general rule that you add
oil at all three stages, which is what we say by the
other מנחות, Minchos here they differ because of which stage do you
add the oil. The חלות challos you add the oil at the
second stage, the mixing, and the רקיקין rekikin you add the oil
at the third stage. So let's take a look. חלות טעונות בלילה
ורקיקין משיחה. Challos te'unos belilah ve'rekikin meshichah. The חלות challos you add,
you add the oil at the second stage, the mixing, and the
רקיקין rekikin you anoint it at the third stage after you've baked
it. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So here on the פסוק. חלות בלולות,
Challos belulos, the חלות challos are mixed with oil, the flour is
mixed with oil, ולא רקיקין בלולין, velo rekikin belulin, but not the
רקיקין, rekikin, not the רקיקין בלולין. rekikin belulin. Now what it's going
to do is it's going to basically say, why not just learn
one from the other? The same way we apply all the oil
stages from the מנחה mincha. and from the מרחשת Marcheshes and the
מחבת, Machvas why don't we apply all of the different oil stages
from the different types of חלות challos and say, you know, both
חלות challos you both mix it with flour, the flour with the
oil, and you pour the oil at the final stage? The basic
answer is because then they won't be different from one another, but
okay, let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara, says, תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan. חלות בלולות, challos belulos, the חלות challos are mixed, the flour
is mixed with oil, ולא רקיקין בלולין, velo rekikin belulin, but not
the רקיקין, rekikin, their dough is not mixed with oil. שיכול ולא
דין הוא? Sheyachol velo din hu? It really would stand to argue
as logic, and you could make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה
חלות שאינן טעונות משיחה טעונות בלילה, Umah challos she'einam te'unos meshichah te'unos
belilah, if by the חלות challos. you don't do the anointing with
oil at the end, nevertheless you mix the dough with oil, רקיקין
שטעונים משיחה, rekikin she'te'unim meshichah, the רקיקין rekikin that you do the
anointing of oil at the end, אינו דין שטעונות בלילה? eino din
she'te'unos belilah? How much more so should you have to do the
second stage with oil? Of course, you know, that assumes that you
make קל וחומר kal vachomers as in things that things are distinct.
Anyway, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar חלות בלולות, challos belulos, the חלות challos
are mixed, ולא רקיקין בלולין, velo rekikin belulin, the רקיקין rekikin are
not, their dough is not mixed with oil. Now we're going to
say the opposite. רקיקין משוחים ולא חלות משוחות. Rekikin meshuchim velo challos
meshuchos. The רקיקין rekikin are anointed with oil, but not the חלות.
chalos. שיכול ולא דין הוא? Sheyachol velo din hu? I might have
said it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה רקיקין שאינם טעונים בלילה
טעונים משיחה, Umah rekikin she'einam te'unim belilah te'unim meshichah, the רקיקין rekikin
that you don't mix the flour with oil, you nevertheless pour the
oil on at the end, חלות שטעונות בלילה, challos she'te'unos belilah, the
חלות challos, where you mix the flour with oil, אינו דין שטעונות
משיחה? eino din she'te'unos meshichah? How much more so should you
oil at the end, תלמוד לומר רקיקין משוחים. talmud lomar rikikin meshuchin.
It says no, it says the wafers are anointed ולא חלות משוחות
v'lo chalos meshuchos and not the חלות. challos, So then the גמרא
Gemara. finally says מאי תלמודא, mai talmuda, where are you getting this
from the פסוק? At the end of the day, it's true it
says one for one and one for the other, but why not
apply them to each other like we've done by the מחבת Machvas,
and מרחשת, marcheshet, just learn them out from one another? So אמר
רבא, amar Rava, לא לישתמיט קרא, lo lishtamit kra, they add the
word קרא, kra, ולכתוב חלות משוחות ורקיקין בלולים. v'lichtov challos meshuchos v'rikikin
belulim. This is an interesting argument, it's an argument from silence. It's
interesting when the גמרא Gemara does it. לא לישתמיט קרא lo lishtamit
kra means the—it's a hard idiom to translate. It sort of means
like the פסוק would not have left out, meaning like the פסוק
would have never—why don't we ever find that the פסוק ever says
the opposite? Why doesn't it ever refer to
חלות משוחות chalos meshuchos or רקיקין בלולים? rikikin belulim? It only refers
to חלות בלולות chalos belulos and רקיקין משוחים, rikikin meshuchin, so we
should assume essentially an argument from silence that it's exactly that way
and not the other way. But again, it's a very strange type
of an argument from silence. I mean, how about the מחבת and
מרחשת, right? It describes one the oil one way and one the
oil the other way, it never describes them in the opposite, the
only time in the תורה Torah where it describes מחבת and מרחשת,
so we don't say by some argument to silence that you don't
apply one to the other. So the argument of silence is actually,
you know, look, sometimes it has more weight. As we know, if
you expect—like sometimes when somebody tries to make an argument about a
new idea, you know, and the response, and this often happens like
post-גמרא Gemara literature and like the ראשונים Rishonim or the אחרונים, Acharonim,
somebody tries to say, "Oh, well really this is the case," and
everyone says, "Are you kidding? If that was true, how come we
never found it mentioned anywhere? How come nobody ever raised this as
a possibility?" You know, there are times where an argument from silence
is a good one. If people should have been saying this and
they didn't, then the silence is indicative. Here, it's very strange. How
much can you argue from silence if the תורה Torah says it
one place and if just by the next פסוקים Psukim, we apply
one to the next? But it is an interesting phrase to be
aware, לא לישתמיט, lo lishtamit, which
means how come it was never mentioned before is sort of what
that phrase means. Yes, I'm sorry.
No,
so it's a good question, but what's the answer? I mean, what
is the rule for when you can make an argument by silence?
Right. So normally, I mean, it's never fully articulated, but normally it's
when there would have been a reasonable
expectation for it to have been said had it been true. And
the greater the expectation is, then the stronger the argument from silence
is. But in this case, it's pretty weak. Yeah, I don't really
understand the response. Okay. So, so that's how you do the חלה.
challa. Now what we're left with is by the
מרחשת and the מחבת, it says just pour oil on it. But
by the חלות, challos it says משוחים, meshuchin, which literally means anointed.
So here we assume that there's a particular ritual for these רקיקין.
rikikin. Remember, they're baked just water חלות, challos only just simply baked
dough, and then you pour the oil on it afterwards. But it
describes the oil afterwards as משוחים, meshuchin, anointed. So what does that
mean?
So let's take a look. כיצד מושחן? keitzad moshchan? How do you
anoint these רקיקין rikikin for the oven-baked ones? כמין כי, k'min ki,
like a כי, ki, והשאר נאכל v'hashar ne'echal and then it's eaten,
the שיריים. shirayim. מאי כמין כי? mai k'min ki? Says the גמרא,
Gemara what does כמין כי k'min ki mean? אמר רב כהנא כמין
כי יוני, amar Rav Kahana k'min ki Yevani, like the Greek כי,
or how is it pronounced? Chi? Kai? Right, Chi, Kai, which is
an X. Okay. It's actually interesting because רש"י Rashi and תוספות—sometimes Tosafos
רש"י Rashi actually describes that it looks like an X, but if
you look at תוספות Tosafos here, כמין כי, k'min ki, תוספות Tosafos
says, כתב בקונטרס כמין טית, kasav bekuntres k'min tes, בפירושי חומש. bepeirushei
Chumash. Okay, so he says he has a רש"י Rashi that made
it look like a טית, tes, which isn't right. And then he
says,
ובפירושי חומש פירש גימל, ubepeirushei Chumash peireish gimmel, which also isn't right,
although it's closer. If you wanted to think of any Hebrew letter
that looked as close to an X, it probably would be a
גימל, gimmel, because you have one diagonal line and one line like
this, right? It's almost, you know, it's almost an X.
ויש מפרשים כמין נון או כמין כף. veyesh mefarshim k'min nun o
k'min kaf. He didn't really know what it was. Okay, anyway, but
others, I think the רמב"ם Rambam clearly says that it's an X.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan: Now we're going to talk about what
happens by the מנחה mincha. that is—remember, some type of the baked
מנחות Minchos. can be half and half.
There's a question about the baked מנחה. mincha Is it either all
חלות challos, or all רקיקין? rikikin? And then there's the position of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says if you want, you could do
half and half. So this ברייתא braisa is going to be working
with רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's assumption that if you want, the baked
מנחה mincha, could be half and half. Let's take a look.
תנו רבנן מנחה הבאה מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין, tanu rabbanan mincha haba'ah
mechtza challos umechtza rikikin, if you're bringing one that is half חלות
challos and half רקיקין, rikikin, and now we've described the differences when
you add the oil, מביא לוג שמן וחוצהו, meivi log shemen vechotzeihu,
so you bring a לוג, log, that's the amount of oil, which
is, as I said, about fourteen ounces, וחוצהו, vechotzeihu, split it in
half. חציו לחלות, chetzyo lachallos, half you do to the חלות, challos.
which is where you're adding the oil. the oil to the dough
stage, וחציו לרקיקין, ve-chetzyo l'rekikin, half to the רקיקין rekikin where you're
going to anoint it after you bake. וחלות בוללה, ve-challos bol'lah, and
חלות challos, you mixed the flour with oil, you make dough with
oil and you bake it. ורקיקין ve-rekikin and the רקיקין rekikin משחן,
moshchan, after they're baked you're going to anoint them with the oil.
ומושח את הרקיק פני כולו, u-mosheach es ha-rekik pnei kulo, you do
this anointing on the top, on the crust, the top of the
whole רקיק rekik loaf.
ושאר השמן, ve-sha'ar ha-shemen, now that's not going to be all your,
you know, your seven ounces. You've got seven ounces here to consume,
you're not going to use it all to make this anointing, so
what do you do with the rest of it? ושאר השמן מחזירו
לחלות, ve-sha'ar ha-shemen machziro l'challos, you add back to the חלות. challos,
Of course that means you have to first bake the רקיקין rekikin
before you bake the חלות, challos. because if you want to add
it back to the חלות, challos, you've got to add it back
into the dough stage. Okay, but it assumes that you're going to
have left over, and what you do with what's left over is
you put it back into the
חלות. challos, רבי שמעון בן יהודה משום רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda mishum Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda in the name of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: מושחן
כמין כי, moshchan kamin chi, no, you anoint it like this X,
okay, which is if all you're going to do is make an
X, certainly you're going to have a lot of oil left over.
And he says but you don't put the oil back into the
חלות, challos what do you do? ושאר השמן נאכל לכהנים. ve-sha'ar ha-shemen
ne'echal la-kohanim. The rest of the oil is eaten by the כהנים.
kohanim. It's sort of like the לוג שמן log shemen of the
מצורע. metzora. It doesn't really get mixed into the מנחה, Mincha, which
is strange, right? We always assume like it's one thing if you
bring oil separately by the מצורע, metzora, but we always assume that
by the מנחה, Mincha, basically the dough or what the baked product
is the basic thing. These other things are just the ingredients, so
you have to get all the ingredients into the final product. But
he is saying no, here where the idea of oil is anointing
afterwards, you can have oil left over and that's just given separately
to the כהנים, kohanim, it doesn't get actually
incorporated fully into the מנחה. Mincha, תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught
in another ברייתא: braisa: רקיקין הבאין בפני עצמן, rekikin ha-ba'in bifnei atzman,
let's say you're bringing just רקיקין, rekikin, not with חלות, challos it's
a full רקיקין rekikin of the baked, of the baked מנחה. Mincha,
מביא לוג שמן, mevi log shemen, so now you have your full
לוג log of oil. It's even a bigger problem. You've got your
full full 14 ounces of oil, which all you're going to do
is not add them to the flour, but after it's baked you're
going to make this little X on the top of the, on
the top of the loaves. Okay, that's what you'll do after they're
baked, or the loaf. So what do you do? So
ומושחן וחוזר ומושחן עד שיכלה כל השמן שבלוג. u-moshchan ve-chozer u-moshchan ad
she-yichleh kol ha-shemen she-be-log. So the first opinion is you keep on
anointing and anointing and anointing and making your X and pouring the
flour on the top until it all eventually gets absorbed. Okay, so
this is the opinion that obviously the oil had to be fully
incorporated into the מנחה. mincha That is the first opinion. רבי שמעון
בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Shimon, no, מושחן כמין כי, moshchan kamin chi, you just make
your one X, ושאר השמן נאכל לכהנים, ve-sha'ar ha-shemen ne'echal la-kohanim, it
doesn't, the rest does not get incorporated, it gets eaten by the
כהנים. kohanim. So now we have the, the, the full stages of
all of the מנחות. menachos Okay, let's talk, let's talk about them
and I see Michael's looking at his book, so you can show
us Michael if it follows the book. So the מנחה mincha, what?
It is a good book. I meant to bring פני שלמה's Pnei
Shlomo's but we'll look at it now. So now that we've gone
the גמרא. Gemara's The מנחת סולת, minchas soles, what? You do, you
put oil in the כלי beforehand, you put flour, then you put
oil, oil in. You, according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, you don't add
water because then you couldn't stop it from becoming חמץ. chametz. So
you do, you mix your dough with flour, do they have water
for for their סולת soles one? Okay, you mix your dough with
flour and oil, and then you basically have a dough מנחה, mincha
and then you do a little pouring of oil afterwards after it
turns into dough. Is that what they have there in the picture?
מתן שמן בלילה יציקה. matan shemen belilah yetzikah.
Okay, do they have pictures? Well, they have, okay, could I, could
I borrow this? Okay, look.
Okay, okay, okay, so you got the oil here, then you have
the flour,
although I don't know, the flour here to me looks like it's
already dough,
then you have the mixing, the mixing with the oil, right? That's
the, so you have the oil ahead of time, then you've got
the, then you've got the flour with oil, then you have the
anointing afterwards. That's very easy, that's the dough. According to the רמב"ם,
Rambam, you didn't have any water there as I said, because otherwise
you couldn't stop it from becoming חמץ. Chametz. Okay, and then the
לבונה levonah and הגשה hagashah etc. Where, where's the next one? Keep
on going.
Did it go in order? Yeah. Did I skip?
No, no, they're just showing, they're showing the rest of it. No,
no.
Okay, where's the m-, oh, okay. They have the, oh, okay, there's
the, okay,
so here's the- oh, skip the
dish, the part that you didn't you wouldn't know.
Oh, okay, I got it. Okay, so here's the, so, so this
is the one, this is the baked one. Now the baked, it
depends if it's חלות challos or רקיקין. rekikin. So first of all,
according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, not only did you not pour oil
at the end, you also didn't put oil in the כלי beforehand.
It's only exactly the way the oil was described in the תורה.
Torah. You don't, you don't learn out anything, you don't do it
according to the רמב"ם. Rambam. תוספות Tosafos disagrees. But you don't learn
out anything from the מחבת and the מרחשת. It's just what it
says by the חלות challos. itself. So you mix the flour with
the oil if it's the חלות Challos and you obviously add water
in order that it could become חלות. Challos, And then that's it,
and then you bake it. Okay, and then you break it up
into pieces and that's it. If it is, however, the, the רקיקין,
rekikin, then you did not add oil beforehand, you just baked it,
you baked it first. and then you did the משיחה, Meshicha, the
X afterwards, although he has it like a נון Nun for whatever
reason, following that other רש"י. Rashi. Okay, anyway, and if it's finally,
if it's this מחבת, oh that's interesting, he's got it like things
with protrusions. Anyway, if it's מחבת or no, or no insertions like
that.
Well, well when is the מרחשת the other's מחבת.
I understood that one was completely flat and the other was sort
of like a deep pan.
Any one you want. What?
You could, you could make, you could do any, you decide, you
decide what you want, right.
That's why I just
don't understand why would they do one rather than the other? So
you weren't here, I know that was a good question, but there
was one day where the גמרא Gemara actually spoke about the symbolic
significance of the different types of מנחות menachos or at least what
they might be, you know, that מרחשת is more like, you know,
has to do maybe more with thoughts because it's bubbling and it's
boiling, you know, that there might be different symbolic. We wouldn't, we
didn't live in their world, we don't know how these things, the
religious way in which these, you know, resonated or symbolized. Okay, so
anyway, so then the מחבת and the מרחשת is all three stages,
like the סולת, Soles, oil in the vessel, flour, then oil, then
water, because it has the possibility of being becoming חמץ. chametz Okay,
then you go ahead and you either fry it on a flat
pan or on a deep pan, and then after it's hardened and
it's fried, you break it into pieces and then you pour the
oil on afterwards. Okay, now let's get on to our next משנה.
Mishna. כל המנחות הנעשות בכלי טעונות פתיתה. Kol HaMinchos HaNa'asos B'Kli Te'unos
Pesisa. All מנחות that are made in a vessel, you need to
break it into pieces. Now what is that excluding? Well first of
all I should say one thing you're not breaking into pieces is
the flour one because you can't because it's just flour, I mean
it doesn't say פתות אותה פתים. Posos Osa Pesim. Okay, but so
what is this going to exclude? So the גמרא Gemara says למעוטי
מאי, L'ma'utei Mai, what does this exclude? אמר רב פפא למעוטי שתי
הלחם ולחם הפנים. Amar Rav Papa L'ma'utei Shtei HaLechem V'Lechem HaPanim. The
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, those you do
not. Now one of the reasons you don't buy them is because
one of the purposes of פתיתה Pesisa is to do קמיצה, Kemitza,
that you break it into pieces so you can grab it and
do קמיצה, Kemitza, which is why you don't need פתיתה Pesisa by
the by the dough one because you know it's easier to just
do a קמיצה Kemitza of dough. Okay, so the לחם הפנים Lechem
HaPanim and the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you don't do קמיצה Kemitza
on them. The לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim you burn the לבונה Levona
and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem you bring the lambs of the
עצרת, Atzeres, the כבשי עצרת. Kivsei Atzeres. So there you do not
do פתיתה. Pesisa. Okay, so let's see how the גמרא Gemara. though
learns it out. תנו רבנן. פתות
אותה פתים, Posos Osa Pesim, okay, this is by the מרחשת again,
פתות אותה פתים Posos Osa Pesim המחבת, break it into pieces. מנחה
היא, Mincha Hi, it says it is a מנחה, mincha לרבות כל
המנחות לפתיתה, L'rabos Kol HaMinchos L'pesisa, you do this for all the
מנחות. יכול שאני מרבה אפילו Yachol She'ani Marbeh Afilu the you know
oven one and even the מחבת and even the מרחשת one, even
the ones that it doesn't say it. Okay, יכול שאני מרבה שתי
הלחם ולחם הפנים, Yachol She'ani Marbeh Shtei HaLechem V'Lechem HaPanim,
maybe I apply it even to the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and
לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. תלמוד לומר אותה, Talmud Lomar Osa, only it,
so that's a limiting פסוק, so we'll say in a minute how
I know what things to exclude. ויצקת עליה שמן V'yatzakta Aleha Shemen
and then you pour oil on it. This is again by the
מחבת. מנחה היא, Mincha Hi, it is a מנחה, mincha לרבות כל
המנחות ליציקה, L'rabos Kol HaMinchos L'yetzika, you pour oil on everything. יכול
שאני מרבה אף מנחת מאפה, Yachol She'ani Marbeh Af Minchas Ma'afeh,
maybe even the oven baked. This is what we just said before,
you don't pour oil at the end of the oven baked, especially
if it's the חלות Challos certainly not. Okay, תלמוד לומר עליה שמן,
Talmud Lomar Aleha Shemen,
only on
it.
הוציא את החלות, Hotzi Es HaChallos, so I'll exclude the חלות, Challos.
אבל לא הוציא את הרקיקין, Aval Lo Hotzi Es HaRekikin,
maybe the רקיקין Rekikin that you do משיחה, Meshicha, you'll also do
just a simple pouring even in addition to the משיחה. Meshicha. תלמוד
לומר היא. Talmud Lomar Hi. So okay, so therefore here we basically
say, which is the גמרא's Gemara again going to note the problem,
from the מחבת and the מרחשת we learn the three stages of
oil, we also learn the breaking into pieces. Then when it comes
to how broadly do we apply it, so the breaking into pieces
we apply to everything, even the oven baked, we just don't apply
to the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim.
The applying of oil we apply even less, we don't even apply
to the oven baked. So what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי תלמודא, Mai Talmudah, what is the derivation? How do you
decide one thing has a broader scope than the other and narrower
scope? אימא להוציא מנחת כהנים, Eima L'hotzi Minchas Kohanim, maybe actually if
we're excluding things, maybe we're not even excluding שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים,
Shtei HaLechem V'Lechem HaPanim, maybe we're excluding the כהנים's Kohanim's מנחה, mincha
you know מנחת כהנים Minchas Kohanim is treated differently, that you burn
the whole thing, so maybe here too. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so רבא Rava says איזהו דבר שצריך שני מיעוטין הוי אומר זה
מנחת מאפה. Eizehu Davar Shetzarich Shnei Mi'utin Hevei Omer Zeh Minchas Ma'afeh.
No, because when it speaks about the oil, there are two מיעוטין.
Mi'utin. It says and it says like this by the מחבת, it
says ואם מנחה על המחבת קרבנך סלת בלולה בשמן מצה פתות אותה
פתים, V'im Mincha Al HaMachvas Korbanacha Soles Blulah VaShemen Matza Posos Osa
Pesim, so פתות אותה פתים Posos Osa Pesim is only one מיעוט,
Mi'ut, אותה, Osa, it's only limiting one thing, so it's limiting the
categories of שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים. Shtei HaLechem V'Lechem HaPanim. But then
when it comes to the oil, it says ויצקת עליה שמן, V'yatzakta
Aleha Shemen, on it, which is one limiting word, מנחה היא, Mincha
Hi, it is a מנחה, mincha which is the second limiting word.
So what type of thing has two components that have to be
limited, it is the מאפה תנור that has two components, it has
the חלות and the רקיקין. Rekikin. In the end of the day
obviously you can't get this straight from the פסוקים, you have to
have certain assumptions coming in. So the assumption is like this, since
the תורה Torah by the oven describes the oil as different for
the you know for the רקיקין Rekikin and the חלות. where we're
not going to learn out oil from other places. We're going to
assume that the oil by the oven baked is as it is
described in the תורה; Torah; we're not going to learn it out
from the other places. Now why do we not do the breaking
up for the why don't we learn out the פתיטה ptita to
apply to the שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים? shtei halechem lechem hapanim? How
do we know to exclude them? So one point that I made,
that is also made not just me, רש''י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, whatever,
is that you don't have to do קמיצה. kmitza. And part of
the main function of פתיטה ptita is to allow for קמיצה; kmitza;
you don't do קמיצה kmitza by שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים. shtei halechem
lechem hapanim. The other possibility that רש''י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
say is that שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim are
communal sacrifices. So therefore as communal sacrifices, and the combination that it's
both communal so it's not fundamentally in this פרשה, parsha, this פרשה
parsha is about individual, and it's the combined fact that it's communal
and that there's no need to do קמיצה, kmitza, both of those
lead to saying that you don't do פתיטה. ptita. By the way,
עומר Omer is an עומר Omer is a communal that you do
do פתיטה ptita because עומר Omer is something you do קמיצה. kmitza.
But it's the combination of them both not being in this פרשה
parsha because they're communal and that you don't really need to do
פתיטה ptita because there's not going to be קמיצה. kmitza. Okay, so
now we have this idea that other than the dough and the
שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים, shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim, what do you do
with all things? You bake them, you fry them, after you bake
and fry them, you break them into pieces, pour some oil on
them, if it's not the oven baked one, you pour some oil
on them and then you do the קמיצה. kmitza. And now let's
take a look at the next משנה mishna about how you do
the פתיטה. ptita. מנחת ישראל, Minchat Yisrael, a מנחה mincha, of a
ישראל Yisrael meaning not of a כהן, Kohen, because a כהן Kohen
you burn the whole מנחה, mincha so you don't have to do
פתיטה ptita for a מנחה mincha of a כהן, Kohen, right? Just
burn the whole thing. But מנחת ישראל, כופל אחד לשנים ושנים לארבע.
Minchat Yisrael kofel echad lishnayim ushnayim l'arbah, You take your baked product,
whether it is a, you know, a loaf, maybe more like a
maybe more like a what do you call it? More like a
pita, thank you, or whether it's like some fried bread, okay, you
take whatever you've baked or fried, you fold it into half, ושנים
לארבע, v'shnayim l'arba, halves into quarters, so you break it into basically
four pieces, ומבדיל, v'mavdil, and you, you know, you separate it as
you break it. So now you have four pieces, equally divided pieces.
That's how you do your פתיטה. ptita. Now it's a little strange
because I would think that those pieces are still too big to
do a good קמיצה kmitza on. I would think to do to
do a קמיצה kmitza you need smaller pieces. Like if I've baked
something and I just fold it, like how am I going to
really do a good and maybe I make a lot of separate
loaves, so for each loaf I divide into quarters, then I could
still do a good קמיצה kmitza from the pieces. But if I
make one big loaf and I have a quarter of it, it's
not exactly clear to me how you're doing a קמיצה. kmitza. מנחת
כהנים, Minchat Kohanim, כופל אחד לשנים ושנים לארבע ואינו מבדיל. kofel echad
l'shnayim v'shnayim l'arba v'eino mavdil.
The מנחה mincha of the כהנים Kohanim there is an idea of
doing a פתיטה ptita interestingly, but you don't separate it because you
don't have to do a קמיצה kmitza and then you're going to
burn it fully. So that's a little interesting middle stage. You do
the you do the folding over, but you don't break the pieces
off because you're ultimately going to burn the whole thing whole. מנחת
כהן משיח, Minchat Kohen Mashiach, now the מנחה mincha of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol which you would bring half in the morning, half
in the afternoon, לא היה מקפלה. lo haya mekapla. He would not
fold it at
all. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer well,
because it's going to but it describes his מנחה mincha. as we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara the תורה Torah when it describes his
מנחה mincha calls it
it calls it it calls it מנחת פתים. minchat pitim. It doesn't
say פתות אותה פתים, patot otah pitim, but actually, if anything, that
leads to the next position, which is that you did fold it
but not as much. Okay, when the תורה Torah describes the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol's מנחה, mincha it says,
תפיני מנחת פתים תקריב ריח ניחוח לה'. tufinei minchat pitim takriv reiach
nichoach l'Hashem. So it actually does say it as a מנחה mincha,
of pieces, so you are right that the first position that you
didn't fold it at all is strange, but let's look at I
don't know, but let's look at the second one.
כהן משיח לא היה מקפלה. Kohen Mashiach lo haya mekapla. רבי שמעון
אומר מנחת כהנים מנחת כהן משיח אין בהם פתיטה. Rabbi Shimon omer
minchat kohanim minchat kohen mashiach ein bahem ptita. You would not fold
them at all, not only of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol but
even of the normal כהנים Kohanim מפני שאין בהם קמיצה. mipnei she'ein
bahem kmitza. Because there's no קמיצה. kmitza. וכל שאין בה קמיצה אין
בהם פתיטה. V'chol she'ein ba kmitza ein bahem ptita. So you wanted
to take a middle position for the כהנים: Kohanim: fold it but
don't break it. Fold it and then put it. If you're not
going to break it, why are you folding it? Don't do anything,
just burn the whole thing. וכולן, v'chulan, and same by מנחה mincha?
of כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Why fold, why break? You're not going
to burn it. וכולן פותתין כזיתים. V'chulan potetin kezaitim. And רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says, I also don't agree with you that you break
it only into quarters. I think you break it into smaller pieces.
I think you break it into the fact that each piece should
have basically the size of an olive. That makes sense. Now you
can understand how you do קמיצה. kmitza. So what it really seems
is that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is very focused on this as
a means of קמיצה. kmitza. Because for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's
a means of קמיצה kmitza it leads to both of his positions.
One position is you need small pieces. If you want to do
קמיצה kmitza with this you need small pieces, you can't have big
chunks. And number two is, if it's about קמיצה, kmitza, a מנחת
כהנים minchat Kohanim where there's no קמיצה, kmitza, there's no point of
that doing anything of it. Whereas the חכמים Chachamim apparently hold there's
a sense of doing פתיטה ptita even when it's not based on
קמיצה. kmitza. So let's take a look about that in the גמרא.
Gemara תנו רבנן: פתות, break it, this is again by the מרחשת,
פתות אותה פתים, patot otah pitim, from, you know, break it into
pieces. יכול לשנים, yachol l'shnayim, maybe just two pieces? תלמוד לומר: Talmud
lomar: פתים, pitim, it could have just said פתות. פתות אותה פתים
patot otah pitim means again again, so another breaking. אי פתים יכול
יעשנה פרורין, Ee petim yachol yaasennah perurin, maybe you make it into
crumbs, tiny little pieces? תלמוד לומר אותה, Talmud lomar otah, it would
have to retain its integrity. אותה לפתים Otah lepitim and not only
that, the breaking is of the original. The original thing has to
be broken into pieces ולא פתיתיה לפתים v'lo ptiteha l'pitim and don't
break the pieces into pieces. So only divide the original into pieces,
not the pieces into pieces. Okay, so הכיצד, Hakeitzad, so how do
you do it? מנחת ישראל Minchat Yisrael, כופל אחד לשנים ושנים לארבע,
kofel echad l'shnayim v'shnayim l'arba. one into two and two into four,
that's your double. פתות אותה פתים Patot otah pitim ומבדיל umavdil and
then you break it and then you separate it. מנחת כהנים וכהן
משיח היה מקפל, Minchat kohanim v'kohen mashiach haya mekappel, you would fold
it, but you would not break
it. Now actually this actually is interesting here, it says וכהן משיח
v'kohen mashiach is like the מנחת כהנים. minchat kohanim. It's a third
opinion, right? We didn't have in the, we didn't have in our
משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah said you would fold the normal מנחת
כהנים minchat kohanim but not of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Here
it says the normal and the כהן גדול kohen gadol you would
fold. Okay, והתנן לא היה מקפל v'ha tnan lo haya mekappel and
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Our משנה Mishnah says you would
not fold the מנחה mincha? of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, how
come here it says you do fold it? אמר רבא אינו מקפל
לארבע אבל מקפל לשנים. Amar Rava eino mekappel l'arbah aval mekappel lishnayim.
Enough for you,
הרי זו. Haray zo. All right, take care. Okay, so he says
you would not fold it into four, you would fold it into
two. So this actually answers, you know, my question, well why wouldn't
you fold it at all? So here what it's saying is like
this. By the כהן גדול kohen gadol it says תופיני מנחת פתים.
tufinei minchat pitim. It says the word פתים pitim once, it doesn't
say פתות אותה פתים. patot otah pitim. So the way we explain
the כהן גדול kohen gadol is we say, ah, פתים, but not
פתות אותה פתים, patot otah pitim, so therefore you only do it
one fold, you make two pieces. כהן גדול, kohen gadol, you don't
do four folds. Our משנה Mishnah says you don't do it, means
you don't do the full amount, you don't do four. The ברייתא
Baraita says you do it, means you do something, you do two.
So they both agree?
Yes, they're reconciling the משנה Mishnah and the ברייתא. Baraita. Now what
still is strange is again for the חכמים, Chachamim, this is important,
this is their basic difference with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, is that
they think the folding is not just about the קמיצה. kmitza. The
way you know it is number one, they had it by the
כהן גדול kohen gadol and they had it by a normal כהן.
kohen. They had you folding a normal כהן's kohen into four. Don't
break it, you don't have to, the breaking is to achieve the
קמיצה kmitza but still you do it by a normal כהן kohen
even though there's no קמיצה. kmitza. So also why again they don't
emphasize that it should be small pieces. Again, I'm not speaking.
So what did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
do with this פתים then? I don't know, that's a good question.
You're right, I don't know, I don't know how he explains it.
Maybe originally you bake it as separate units or something. Okay, let's
take a
look. רבי שמעון אומר מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח אין בהם פתיתה,
Rabbi Shimon omer minchat kohanim uminchat kohen mashiach ein bahem ptita, you
do not break it because the breaking is all about the קמיצה.
kmitza. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, now we actually, too bad
that we, that some people had to go by now because now
we actually finally after all of these details turn to a really
relevant הלכה. Halacha. האי חביצא דאית ביה פרורין
כזית מברכינן עליה המוציא לחם מן הארץ. Hai chavitza d'it beh perurin
kezayit mivarchinan aleha hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz. Okay, so look at that,
whoa, where was that coming from? Actually it's straight from the גמרא
Gemara in ברכות. Brachot. Okay, but it was imported here. So you
have this חביצא, chavitza, it's a question what this means. רש"י Rashi
says it's a type of a baked or cooked product that you
have bread crumbs in it and then you cook. תוספות Tosafot says
from the later גמרא Gemara it is clear, I'm
sorry, it's made of bread crumbs?
You bread crumbs and oil or whatever else you do, some type
of a thing with this mixed bread crumbs and then you bake
it or you cook it. תוספות Tosafot says from the later גמרא
Gemara it's clear that you didn't bake it or cook it because
it's going to compare it to what the מנחה mincha is, which
is the broken up little pieces mixed with oil. So therefore, and
תוספות Tosafot says if you cook it afterwards that could totally transform
the ברכה bracha and that's a different conversation. So we're going to
go with תוספות's Tosafot's assumption which is that it's bread crumbs in
some type of a honey mixture or an oil mixture and it
has not been cooked or baked again. Okay, so here's the question,
what is the הלכה ברכה halacha bracha when you take bread crumbs,
you know, and you make something with it without baking? It's also
a question like when you have your little croutons or not croutons,
whatever they're called, in your salad, that's croutons, croutons, the real croutons,
not those fake things that they sell, whatever, real bread crumb croutons,
what do you have to make a המוציא Hamotzi or not? So
there it's not combined into one unit, but maybe it is conceptually.
Wait, so is רש"י Rashi talking about something like let's say breaded
cauliflower?
Not exactly, he's talking about more some mixture, but I don't want
to go into רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so anyway, we're not learning ברכות
Brachot now, okay, we're just going to learn what we have here.
Okay, so you have your bread crumbs in some type of a
mixture. Do, what, do you get a המוציא Hamotzi if it's bread
crumbs mixed with other stuff? So he says, this חביצא chavitza which
תוספות Tosafot
says
is honey and bread crumbs, it's like you've got bread crumbs stuck
together with honey. Okay, you make if each of the crumbs is
a כזית kezayit then you could still make a המוציא. Hamotzi. Presumably
if not you'd maybe make a מזונות, Mezonot, okay, but if the
each once still retains a כזית kezayit then you can make a
המוציא. Hamotzi.
Oh, it means each
crumb?
Yes, each crumb. The פרורין perurin are כזית. kezayit. Okay, but you
know, like croutons, it's not, I mean a כזית kezayit is a
real כזית, kezayit, not one of our כזית. kezayit. Okay, anyway, all
right, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי לית בה
פרורין כזית, Ee leit bah perurin kezayit, if the size of the
of the pieces are not a כזית kezayit מברכינן עליה בורא מיני
מזונות mivarchinan aleh borei minei mezonot and you make a מזונות. mezonot.
אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. Says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, מנא
מנא לה, mina mina la, where do I get this idea from?
דתניא, detanya, תנא ברייתא, tana braisa, היה עומד ומקריב מנחות בירושלים, haya
omeid umakriv menachos beYerushalayim,
this is a fascinating ברייתא, braisa, somebody is offering up מנחות in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. There's a מחלוקת, machlokes, a מחלוקת, machlokes, רש"י Rashi has
two opinions whether this means the כהן kohen or the ישראל. Yisrael.
Okay, and it's interesting because we'll see in a minute. אומר, omer,
ברוך שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. Baruch shehecheyanu vekiyemanu vehigiyanu lazman hazeh.
You make a שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. So first of all, that's amazing. When
do you ever hear that somebody makes a שהחיינו shehecheyanu when they're
bringing a קרבן? korban. So it must be, what, well, it's a
ברייתא, braisa, it's a series of ברייתות braisas also says if it's
other קרבנות korbanos as well. It just happens to be talking about
a מנחה. mincha So whoever, whoever thought we'd be making a שהחיינו?
shehecheyanu? So it could be, it's very nice. So it could be,
someone wants to say maybe it's just a מנחה mincha because מנחות
were more rare, but תוספות Tosafos points out no, the ברייתא braisa
makes clear it's for other קרבנות korbanos as well. And תוספות Tosafos
says basically, and there's a question also, is it the ישראל Yisrael
or is it the כהן? kohen? So תוספות Tosafos says maybe it's
the כהן kohen and he points out the point as I pointed
out to you before, that the כהנים, kohanim, any individual כהן kohen
really only worked two times a year. Right? He worked if you're
on a rotation and your family only works once every twenty-four weeks,
and within your house, I should say, your family works only one
of those days of those weeks, you're only basically working two times
a year. So תוספות Tosafos says actually, because it's interesting about שהחיינו.
shehecheyanu. On the one hand שהחיינו shehecheyanu is about things that you
sort of don't normally expect, but there's a big שמחה simcha when
they happen. You buy a house, you buy a car, something like
that. The other time you make שהחיינו shehecheyanu are by things that
are actually cyclical and seasonal. So תוספות Tosafos wants to put this
into the second category. He says since it regularly happens twice a
year, so it doesn't happen every day, but it happens in a
cyclical way, that's why you're making this שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. But you could
have said, you know, it's just rare, rarer not because of its
cyclical nature. This is staying with the ישראל? Yisrael? Right. So it's
also an interesting question about whether the ישראל Yisrael is making it,
you know, which is always the question. How much do you view
when you give over the קרבן korban? that you're still doing it
or not? It's sort of like the question whether the כהנים kohanim
are שלוחי דרחמנא shluchei derachmana or שלוחי דידן, shluchei didan, are they
seen as our representatives? How much are we doing, are we involved?
Our emphasis has totally been on the כהנים, kohanim, but you know,
for the people bringing the קרבנות, korbanos, it's because they're, you know,
it's their thing, they're bringing the קרבן. So that question of who's
making a שהחיינו shehecheyanu is a fascinating.
Does he have a שהחיינו shehecheyanu on the זבחים, zevachim, we've already
made the שהחיינו shehecheyanu on the קרבן?
No, I don't think so. Okay, anyway, so that was just parenthetically
fascinating, that you say שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. Then נטלן ואכלן, natlan veachlan, if
you take it to eat it, which is why it sounds like
we're talking about the כהן kohen because clearly now the only person
eating the מנחה mincha, is the כהן, kohen, so it sounds like
the first part is the כהן. kohen. Take it to eat it,
אומר המוציא לחם מן הארץ. omer hamotzi lechem min haaretz. So the
כהן kohen is eating his מנחה, mincha what ברכה bracha does he
make? המוציא. hamotzi. Now, what do we know about the מנחה? דתנן,
detnan, what's מנחה? וכולן פותתן כזית, vechulan potasan kezayis, assuming like we're
going like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that it could be even a
small as a כזית, kezayis, so you'd break it into little pieces
the size of a כזית, kezayis, and then what did you do
afterwards? You poured oil on it, right? If it was just tiny
little pieces then it's just little pieces of bread, but then we
learn from the previous משנה, mishna, after you broke it you poured
oil on it. So here you have little pieces of bread that
are each one of the כזית kezayis combined by oil and you're
making המוציא. hamotzi. So that's where he says I get my idea
from. Okay, אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye says, לתנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, letana devei Rabbi Yishmael, one minute. You can't prove
it from that because we have a third תנא tana from the
house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael not mentioned in our משנה mishna
that says they were even made into smaller sizes. What does he
say? דאמר מפרכן עד שמחזירן לסולתן. damar mefarchan ad shemachziran lesoltan. He
says you do the, you break up a מנחה to so many
small, to such small pieces that you basically make it flour again.
You really break it, מצה מעל, matzah mel, you break it up
into tiny, tiny pieces again. So according to him,
הכא נמי דלא מברך המוציא, hacha nami delo mevarech hamotzi, so would
you say according to him the כהן kohen wouldn't make a המוציא
hamotzi ברכה bracha on it? So why not? דכי תימא הכא נמי,
dechi teima hacha nami, maybe that's true. Maybe if he broke it
up into tiny little מצה מעל matzah mel as you say, you
know, or bread, real breadcrumbs, tiny little breadcrumbs, maybe you wouldn't make
a המוציא hamotzi anymore. So he says, והתניא, vehatanya, we taught it
in a ברייתא, braisa, ליקט מכולן כזית, liket mikulan kezayis, if you
combined all of the crumbs to make a כזית, kezayis, ואכלו, vaachalo,
and you ate it, אם חמץ הוא ענוש כרת, im chametz hu
anash kareis, if it's חמץ chametz. you get כרת kareis and we're
not talking about a מנחה because a מנחה can't be חמץ. chametz
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos don't exactly know what the original context
of this ברייתא braisa is, but whatever it is, תוספות Tosafos thinks
it's referring to the context of the חמש מיני דגן. chamesh minei
dagan. That if you take flour from the חמש מיני דגן chamesh
minei dagan and put them all together, if it's חמץ and it's
פסח Pesach you get כרת. kareis. אם מצה היא, im matzah hi,
and if it's מצה Matzah אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. adam
yotzei bo yedei chovato bePesach. So anyway, what do you see? You
see you have a lot of crumbs, you can eat מצה Matzah
crumbs and if you're eating כזית, kezayis, you're יוצא yotzei your מצוה.
mitzvah. Presumably it means that the crumbs, even as crumbs, still combine
to be considered bread, to be יוצא yotzei מצה Matzah. and to
make a ברכה. bracha. So הכא נמי. hacha nami. Now, of course,
so גמרא Gemara says one minute, הכא במאי עסקינן בשעירסן. hacha b'mai
askinan b'she'ersan. גמרא Gemara says no, no, no. When is that that
you can still make a ברכה bracha about,
I mean that you can still be יוצא yotzei מצה when you
take the little pieces? It's when you actually added water to it.
You had all of your מצה crumbs, even if you didn't rebake
it, at least you made it into some type of a coherent
dough. Okay? רש"י Rashi doesn't say bake it, but anyway you made
it back into עיסה שלמה. aisa shleima. So the גמרא says one
minute, אי הכי, ei hachi, היינו דקתני עלה, hainu de'katni ala, והוא
שאכלן בכדי אכילת פרס. vehu she'achlan bichdei achilas pras. Is that a
motzi?
Is that what you're saying?
Means it's more like it's more one unit.
You have a lot of breadcrumbs, you add water, it's more one
unit, then maybe he says I can agree המוציא. Hamotzi. But if
it's separate breadcrumbs, no.
So like let's say it's soup and I add in all my
breadcrumbs, am I making a motzi?
Is that what you're saying?
No, no, no, not talking about that, no.
A little water, it's co... yeah, right. Just to make it into
dough. Essentially into a dough again. So the גמרא says no, you
can't limit it to dough, to that case. The ברייתא braisa says
והוא שאכלן בכדי אכילת פרס vehu she'achlan bichdei achilas pras that you
have to eat all these little pieces in the amount of time
of eating a half a loaf of bread, whatever that is, four
minutes, nine minutes, anyway.
ואי בשעירסן, v'ei b'she'ersan, if we're only talking about that you mixed
them and made it into dough again, so שאכלה she'achalah מבעי ליה,
mibaei leh, it should have said you eat it, because now it's
one unit, it's dough. So anyway, what do you see from this
ברייתא? braisa? If you eat a lot of little breadcrumbs, you can
make המוציא, Hamotzi, you can be יוצא yotzei מצה. So therefore, even
if they're separate crumbs and less than a כזית, kezayis, they retain
their ברכה, bracha, they retain their identity. So why did you insist
that it require a כזית? kezayis? Now, I would have thought the
answer was that it's better when they're their original and there's no
other ingredient added, or the most other ingredient is water and making
it a dough. If you're mixing the breadcrumbs though with some other
serious ingredient like oil or honey, you know, there you need more
to... you need to work harder to retain your original identity and
therefore maybe you need more of a size. That's not what the
גמרא is saying. It's saying from here we see that even if
they're small pieces less than a כזית, kezayis, you would still make
the ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא says אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela
hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about?
בבא מלחם גדול. b'va milechem gadol. If it's coming from what used
to be a big loaf, then you're going to make a המוציא
Hamotzi even if they're tiny sizes. If you're talking that it was
never a big loaf, then you need it to be a כזית
kezayis to make a המוציא. Hamotzi. Which by the way means that
our case of the מנחה, מנחה clearly came from a big loaf.
It started off larger. So you're going to make a המוציא Hamotzi
from that and you don't need it to be a כזית. kezayis.
So this requirement that you need a כזית kezayis to be המוציא
Hamotzi is only in the original loaf. But once you started with
המוציא, Hamotzi, even if now it's crumbs, you'll still make a המוציא.
Hamotzi. If you take your חלה, challah, you want to like pick
a little bit, you have to make המוציא. Hamotzi.
Right. מאי הוי עלה, mai hava ala, what was the conclusion? רב
ששת Rav Sheshes אמר, amar, אפילו פירורין שאין בהן כזית, afilu perurin
she'ein bahen kezayis, you make a המוציא Hamotzi even on crumbs that
do not have a כזית. kezayis. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, and here
is the key line that is the hardest criteria to apply for
ברכות, brachos, והוא דאיכא תוריתא דנהמא עלייהו. vehu d'ika toresa denahama alaihu.
It only if it has the shape of bread. So you only
make a המוציא Hamotzi on something that has the shape of bread.
What the heck does that mean? It means as we know, there's
things that are made with flour and water which you wouldn't call
bread. We call them things like crackers and pretzels, which have the
exact same ingredients as bread. Why don't we make a המוציא Hamotzi
on them? Because of this criteria that it's not just ingredients, it
has to look like bread. What the heck looks like bread? How
do you determine that is a big, big question. But anyway, what
we are now saying is, to make a המוציא Hamotzi it has
to be flour and water of course, it has to look like
bread, then when it starts off as a כזית kezayis you'll make
a המוציא Hamotzi even if you're dealing with a lot smaller pieces
afterwards.